# **WAEL ALMATTAR**

## **FULL-STACK SOFTWARE DEVELOPER**

Current address: Angerburger allee 53/7, 14055 berlin waelsy123@gmail.com | +49 1525 1969 461 - http://waelalmattar.com/

-----

Highly motivated, pro-active and ambitious freelance Senior Software Engineer who is instinctively entrepreneurial. Agile evangelist. Strong personality and leadership abilities. Experienced in managing international and distributed teams. Open minded and bright with 8 years of experience in web development, performance optimization and architecture design. Lives and breathes software development.

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### **Lead Backend and Microservices Engineer**

**Techloop.io**Sep 2018 – present

#### Responsibilities:

- Developed backend for a platform serves 100k users and 12k companies.
- Took responsible as a lead programmer for the whole backend infrastructure including microservices and RESTful APIs.
- Worked with the team to develop full stack with microservices third-party solutions
- Consulted the business team to draw a reliable road map
- Worked closely with the analytics team to provide rich source of data
- Proposed a simplified but scalable system architecture that is being used at the moment in the production environment.
- Introduced GraphQL to the platform and worked with the frontend team to integrate it.
- Used automated solutions to accelerate the development process.
- Extended the existing API with more features and functionalities.
- Tracked tasks, features and bugs with Jira and Axana.
- Implemented data driven approach to support the marketing and sales teams.
- Created one page application with React is with custom components on top of MUI v4.
- Worked with the business development manager on breaking down new business models to realistic technical tasks with clear roadmap.

**skills**: Node.js, Graphql, Microservices, Typescript, RESTful APIs, Git, Koa, RabbitMQ, ElasticSearch, React.js, PostgreSQL, CronJobs, Docker, antd, auth0, algolia, segment, material-ui, unit test, heroku workers, kubernetes

#### Senior Full-Stack Node.js | System architect

Yara Digital Labs

Nov 2019 - April 2020

Berlin, Germany

#### Responsibilities:

- Worked with engineering managers to construct the new team to build a new platform which is being used by Yara' sales team in more than 10 countries.
- Constructed a project with Typescript, GraphQL and Caching using Redis on Backend. And React.js with Material UI and frontend.
- Consulted the business team to draw a reliable road map.
- Worked mainly as a backend developer as a daily routine.
- Interviewed candidates for permanent roles to continue working on the project.
- Worked with the SRE team to ship deployments with CircleCi, docker and kubernetes.

**skills**: Node.js, GraphQL, React, Typescript, Redis, Material-ui, Elastic, Git, unit test, AWS, Docker, Kubernetes

#### React.js Developer

International Committee of the Red Cross (Outsourced via Iosbar Blue infinity)
March 2018 – Sep 2018 (6 months)

Zurich, Swiss

#### Responsibilities:

- Developed a custom CRM system by the International Committee Red Cross.
- Tracked features and fixed bugs using Microsoft's TFS platform and Microsoft PBI.
- The platform has been launched successfully and has been in production used internally by ICRC.
- Provided full unit testing and clear documentation.

**skills**: Node.js, React, Typescript, Material-ui, Git, unit test, AWS, Docker

#### React.js Developer

Dether.io
Jan 2018 - March 2018 (3 month)

Paris, France - remotely

### Responsibilities:

- Leading development an interactive map for users and clients
- Draw a development plan to keep the code well-organised and fully-tested including UI, load, unit, and end-to-end testing
- Full-stack development with React, Redux and Leaflet

skills: Node.js, React, Leaflet, Redux-React, Heroku, lint, CircleCi

#### Lead SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

Vari Solutions
Oct 2017 – April 2018 (7 months)

Greater New York City Area, USA - remotely

#### Responsibilities:

- Working with the core team to grow the main product VariTest
- Development of API platform
- UI, load, unit, and end-to-end testing
- Full-stack implementation for the platform.

skills: Node.js, Cache mem, postgresql, Angularjs, Travis, Heroku, Lint, chai, puppeteer.js, Locust,

#### SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

GlobelT Warsaw, Poland

Mar 2016 to Sep 2017 (19 months)

• Designed a complete platform for GPS tracking devices with live real-time tracking using NodeJS, Socket.io and AngularJS.

- Created and designed encoder/decoder server for handling GPS binary device's data and send commands.
- Optimized web application speed and data structures by combining Memory and Mysql databases.
- Led API development of new eCommerce/Digital platform (PHP and Nodejs)
- Designed a dashboard and complete solution for the chat module of eCommerce project using PHP and AngularJS.
- Maintained existing eCommerce and Digital applications to meet the ever-evolving demands of the business (PHP)
- Implemented online payment system for eCommerce services.
- Created from skratch an interactive Web Conference Video platform for creating video rooms with text and voice using WebRTC technology, socket.io and jQuery.
- Understanding of a huge existing site.
- Used AngularJS as the development framework to build a dashboard a single-page application and to create more interactive front end development.
- Developed a Web-Scraping web application with Entire server side application using Python.
- Formulated and documented technical architecture, components and strategies for mitigating technical challenges.
- Worked with the business to identify the API's, define data schema and document workflows.
- Design and develop Custom Components, workflows and templates.
- Used Git Version Management.
- This Web application is based on oauth2 based Authorization and Authentication.
- Design & develop common platform frameworks on NodeJS. Ex:- logging, rest client, exception handling.
- Developed the entire server side application using NodeJS.
- Used Socket.io RESTful for web service by exchanging JSON data between the applications.

**Skills:** NodeJS, AngularJS, SOCKET.IO, ExpressJS, Redis, PHP, CSS, jQuery, Zend framework, MySQL, Python, WebRTC, loopback.

#### WEB DEVELOPER INTERN

Mamania.pl Warsaw, Poland

July 2014 to September 2014

Implementing new features for online bookstore.

Skills Used:

Zend framework, PHP, MySQL, CSS

## **EDUCATION**

#### JOINT MASTER IN SPACE SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY:

3rd semester | Université Toulouse III - Paul Sabatier Toulouse, France

Sep 2017 to April 2018

2nd semester | Lulea University of Technology Kiruna, Sweden

Feb 2017 to June 2017

1st semester | Julius-Maximilian's University Würzburg, Germany

Oct 2016 to Feb 2017

**Bachelor in Computer Science, GPA 4.1** 

Warsaw University of Technology Warszawa, Poland

Oct 2013 to Feb 2016

**Bachelor in Computer Engineering and Automation** 

Tishreen University Lattakia, Syria Sep 2010

to July 2013

## **AWARDS**

### 2010 - Bronze Medal - Syrian Olympiad in Informatics

competition requires solving problems of an algorithmic nature under time pressure.

#### 2012 - 5th place - Syrian Collegiate Programming Contest

3 members teams contest requires solving problems of an algorithmic nature under time pressure.

# **LANGUAGES**:

English C1 - Arabic Native - Czech B1 - Polish B1 - German A2

# **HOBBIES**:

Skiing, Gymnastics, Chess, Piano, Swimming, Paragliding, Skateboarding